Hello, and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and what we
are going to be learning is how
to find density via displacement.
Now, the displacement method is
probably one of the most common
labs that's done in introductory
chemistry and general chemistry.
It's usually one of the very first
that you will have to do on your own.
Trying to take different measurements
and observations and doing different
calculations and it can be a little scary
the first time But it's just how can you
use the different properties of matter
to your advantage thinking about how
density is an intrinsic property Meaning
that it's unique for each material.
It's generally very different from
one thing to the other And it's not
affected by the amount of matter or mass
that you have So, if I have, let's say
keep adding more and more of a, of a
substance, the density will not change.
So you could have 10 grams of salt
or 10 million grams of salt, and they
would still have the exact same density.
It does not matter because it's
a ratio between mass over volume.
So how
exactly do we use due
to displacement method?
Well, it's kind of a.
It's, it's almost like following a
cookbook recipe when you're doing this.
The first thing you're going to
do is measure the mass of your
object, um, because, and then also
be measuring the volume as well.
Now, when we are doing this to
measure the volume, there are a
couple methods that you can use.
You can just measure it maybe using
rulers and using known formulas.
But like, for example, to solve the
volume of a cube or maybe the volume
of a cylinder or whatever geometric
shape, but sometimes you might have
weird shape things that don't quite
fit a certain conventional norm.
So you have to sometimes use this method.
So and it works for anything,
it could be even a normal
shape, you could still use it.
So what you're going to do, the first
thing is measure the mass of the object.
And then what you're going to
do is take a graduated cylinder.
And fill it with a volume.
Now, how much liquid should
you put in the first time?
The idea about it is that you want
enough volume to submerge the object,
but you don't want too much so that
way it overflows the graduated cylinder
and you can't get a final measurement.
Because you're going to be
measuring the volume twice.
It's about the difference of volume.
So, going back to thinking about this,
so if I have density, we're going to
have our grams or our mass on top.
Now we're going to first measure the
volume, and then what we're then going
to do is then put the object in, drop
it in there, and get a final volume,
and we're going to measure both.
So it's going to be final
minus initial volume.
And that is how we're going to get our
density for this particular problem.
This is going to be our formula
that we're going to use.
So, just to kind of reiterate how
exactly does that look, let's take a
look at a question to try to understand
this, and then we'll, I'll even
illustrate what exactly this looks like.
So, let's say if I have a lump of solid
material, meaning a lump is a really weird
shape, um, and this was found to weigh 76.
2 grams.
So what I did is, I put my lump on the
balance and I saw, okay, this is 76.
2, great.
Now, what I'm going to do is, as you can
see, I have two graduated cylinders here.
I first measured out 50 milliliters,
and I looked at my meniscus to
see that it was exactly on 50.
Now, I'm gonna, I'm gonna slowly drop
my lump into the grad cylinder, and
when it sank to the bottom, I saw
that all of the liquid was displaced.
It was moved.
Why?
Well, that is because this object
has so much volume to it that it's
going to displace all of the liquid.
When that happened, we
originally had 50 mls.
It displaced it to 78.
2, so let's see if we
can find the density.
Let's go through this type of problem.
So the first thing you want to do
is identify what all the important
pieces of information are.
The first thing you saw was, okay,
we had a mass, we had an initial
volume of water, and then we had a
final volume of water in the problem.
So what we're going to do now is
write all those down for ourselves
so we can solve our problem.
So, mass, was 76.
2 grams, initial volume was 50.
0 milliliters, and then
the final volume was 78.
2 milliliters.
Okay, now, when, how are we going, we're
going to put this into our formula, so
density is equal to mass, so that's 76.
2 grams, all over the volume, which
we have to do final minus initial.
Don't forget that, that's probably one of
the most common mistakes students make is
they forget to subtract your two volumes.
When we do that, we will get a, we
will simplify this, so it'd be 76.
2 grams.
and that will be divided by 28.
2 milliliters.
We will put that into our
calculators, and we will get 2.
70 grams per milliliter,
or you could say 2.
70 grams per centimeter cubed,
depending on which unit you prefer.
Both are equivalent to each other.
Don't forget one gram, or
sorry, one centimeter cubed.
is equal to one ml.
That's a really important conversion to
kind of keep in the back of your mind.
So one cc is a milliliter for
all my health science people.
They always hear ccs, right?
That's a milliliter 2.
7.
So what does that mean?
What can we do with that
piece of information?
Well, it allows you to try
to identify what it is.
Remember, density is
an intrinsic property.
It's unique for most substances, right?
That's generally a different value.
You can use it to try to eliminate
or figure out what could it be.
So here I put a list
together of common metals.
That you usually find in most
labs that are easily accessible.
So we want one that's around 2.
7 grams per milliliter.
And what you will see is aluminum is 2.
So that means that our lump
of material is aluminum.
And that would be our final answer.
And that's how you can use the
displacement method to help you.
It's a little short video
just to give you the ideas.
And thank you so much for watching.
Um, if you enjoyed it, please let me know
in the comments or hit that like button.
Okay, y'all, I hope you have a
wonderful day and I'll see y'all later.
Bye now.